Register of the Kni͡az' Nikolaĭ Vladimirovich Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Kni͡az' Nikolaĭ Vladimirovich Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ papers
1799-1984
71026
Hoover Institution Archives
14 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes (8.7 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, notes, genealogical charts, certificates, and photographs relating to the history of the Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ family from the tenth to the twentieth century and to Russian émigré affairs. Consists mainly of drafts of, and working materials for, a genealogical history. Includes photographs of Emperor Nicholas II and Empress Alexandra.
Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ, Nikolaĭ Vladimirovich, kni͡azʹ, 1899-1982.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1971.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Nikolaĭ Vladimirovich Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ was a Russian aristocrat, émigré to Yugoslavia and Switzerland, and interpreter for the Yugoslav delegation to the League of Nations.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Nikolaĭ Vladimirovich Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ papers consist primarily of writings, correspondence, notes, genealogical charts, certificates, and photographs relating to the history of the Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ family from the tenth to the twentieth century and to Russian émigré affairs. The collection includes drafts of, and working materials for, a genealogical history. Includes photographs of Emperor Nicholas II and Empress Alexandra. Of particular interest in the collection are letters written to and from Romanov family members.
Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ family.; Russia--Court and courtiers.; Poland--Court and courtiers.; Russia--Emigration and immigration.; Alexandra, consort of Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1872-1918--Pictorial works.; Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1868-1918--Pictorial works.; Romanov, House of.
- Biographical File, 1918-1977 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Certificates, curriculum vitae, identification cards, immigration and travel papers, and other materials relating to the life and career of Nikolaĭ Vladimirovich Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  See also: Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ Family File.
  - Certificates, 1918-1945 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Includes notarized copy of Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ's baptism certificate.
  - Career records, 1920-1939
    Includes certificates, recommendations, and employment verification letters relating to Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ's diplomatic assignments, arranged chronologically.
    - 1920-1925 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - 1929 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - 1932-1939 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Education records, 1920-1942 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    Includes an extract from diploma of the University of Belgrade.
  - Financial records, 1920-1929 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    Includes Banque Cantonale Vaudoise statements.
  - Identification documents, 1920-1946 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    Includes passport, embarkation orders, various alien registration documents, and residency permits. See also: immigration papers and travel papers.
  - Immigration papers, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - "Personal notes,", 1930-1977 (Box-folder 1: 9-11)
    Includes correspondence, clippings, notes, and genealogy charts. The original order of the files was retained.
  - Travel papers, 1936-1938
    Includes correspondence and receipts related to Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ's trip to his family homestead in Mir, Poland.
    - Correspondence, 1936-1938 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - Receipts, 1936-1938 (Box-folder 1: 13-14)
- Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ Family File, 1902-1963 (Boxes 1-3)
  Includes identification cards, immigration papers, correspondence, and other materials relating to the lives and careers of the Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ family members, arranged alphabetically by name.
  - Prince Andrei (Andre) Vladimirovich file, 1902-1949
    - Certificates, 1902-1949 (Box-folder 1: 15)
      Includes Andrei's birth, baptism, identity, and death certificates.
    - Education and career file, 1926-1932 (Box-folder 1: 16)
      Includes education certificates and employment verification letter.
  - Georges and Jean (Mirski), 1942-1947 (Box-folder 1: 17)
    Includes immigration papers and correspondence.
  - Princess Maria Aleksandrovna (Mirskaia) file, 1923-1963
    - Biographical file, 1924-1963
      - Passports and certificates of identity, 1924-1945 (Box-folder 2: 1)
      - Russian Orthodox Church Abroad award certificate, Belgrade, 1924 (Box-folder 2: 2)
      - Obituary and burial papers, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Correspondence, 1923-1958
      - Anastasia Nikolaevna (Anastasia of Montenegro), Grand Duchess of Russia, 1924-1931
        - 1924-1925 (Box-folder 2: 4)
        - 1926 (Box-folder 2: 5)
        - 1927 (Box-folder 2: 6)
        - 1928 (Box-folder 2: 7)
        - 1930-1931 (Box-folder 2: 8)
      - Dolgorukii, Prince, 1928 (Box-folder 2: 9)
      - Dukhovskaia, Ol'ga, 1946 (Box-folder 2: 10)
      - Elena Vladimirovna, Grand Duchess of Russia, 1931-1956
        - 1931 (Box-folder 2: 11)
        - 1947 (Box-folder 2: 12)
        - 1949-1950 (Box-folder 2: 13)
        - 1951-1952 (Box-folder 2: 14)
        - 1953-1954 (Box-folder 2: 15)
        - 1955-1956 (Box-folder 2: 16)
      - Feofan, Bishop, 1925 (Box-folder 2: 17)
      - Ksenia (Xenia) Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess of Russia, 1923-1957
        - 1923 (Box-folder 2: 18)
        - 1927-1928 (Box-folder 2: 19)
        - 1929-1930 (Box-folder 3: 1)
        - 1931-1932 (Box-folder 3: 2)
        - 1948-1949 (Box-folder 3: 3)
        - 1950-1951 (Box-folder 3: 4)
        - 1952-1953 (Box-folder 3: 5)
        - 1954-1955 (Box-folder 3: 6)
        - 1956-1957 (Box-folder 3: 7)
      - Militza Nikolaevna (Militza of Montenegro), Grand Duchess of Russia, 1926-1949 (Box-folder 3: 8)
      - Nikolai (Nicholas) Nikolaevich Romanov, Grand Duke of Russia, 1923-1928
        Includes drafts, notes, and envelopes.
        - 1923-1925 (Box-folder 3: 9)
        - 1926-1927 (Box-folder 3: 10)
        - 1928 (Box-folder 3: 11)
      - Nikon, Bishop, 1957 (Box-folder 3: 12)
      - Olga, Princess of Yugoslavia, 1928-1958
        - 1928-1931 (Box-folder 3: 13)
        - 1948-1949 (Box-folder 3: 14)
        - 1951-1952 (Box-folder 3: 15)
        - 1953-1954 (Box-folder 3: 16)
        - 1955-1956 (Box-folder 3: 17)
        - 1957-1958 (Box-folder 3: 18)
      - Orlova, N., 1949 (Box-folder 3: 19)
      - Tat'iana Konstantinovna, Princess of Russia, 1945 (Box-folder 3: 20)
    - Writings, 1926-1937 (Box-folder 3: 21-24)
      Consists primarily of memoirs of Princess Maria Aleksandrovna Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ (Mirskaia), recounting family history. Includes correspondence, notes, and clippings.
  - Prince Vladimir (Mirsky) file, 1948 (Box-folder 3: 25)
    Monthly student progress reports, Grangeneuve Institut agricole de l'Etat de Fribourg.
- Correspondence, 1920-1979 (Boxes 4-5)
  - General, 1920-1970 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Bonnot, Jean de, 1975-1979 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Borowski, Edouard, 1977 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Ferrand, Jacques, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Foire de Paris, 1954 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Galitsyn (Galitzine), Nicholas, 1965-1975 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Gersdorff, Julia, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Gorska, Marycia, 1964-1971 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Gorski, Christophe, 1955-1961 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Gorski, Constantin, 1953 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Hohler, H. A. F., 1966 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Ikonnikoff, Nikolai, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Ilchenko, N., 1965-1971 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Jaccard, Clara, 1938-1972 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Jadvoin, N. L., 1971 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Konarski, Szymon., 1950-1960 (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Lorraine, Percy, 1920 (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - Lyons, Marvin, 1970 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Maksimova (Maximova), Tat'iana (Tania), 1970 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Matthey, Ch. W., 1951-1953 (Box-folder 4: 20)
    Includes references.
  - Nalecz-Gorski, A., 1954-1964 (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - Obolenskii, Sergei, Prince, 1971 (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - Roehrberg (Rerberg), Zinaida N., 1968-1971 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - Shields, Suzanne, 1966 (Box-folder 4: 24)
  - Silina, Ekaterina, 1945 (Box-folder 4: 25)
  - Struve, Aleksei, 1971 (Box-folder 4: 26)
  - Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ
    - Aleksandr, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 4: 27-28)
    - Elena, 1966 (Box-folder 4: 29)
    - Ivan, 1966-1970 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - (Mirskaia), Maria Aleksandrovna, Princess, 1922-1937 (Box-folder 5: 2)
      Includes "Iverskaia Bogomater'" by V. Maevskii, 1932, inscribed by Maria Aleksandrovna for her son Nikolaĭ Vladimirovich.
    - (Mirski), Mikhail (Michal), 1920-1967 (Box-folder 5: 3-4)
    - (Mirsky), Ol'ga, 1963 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - Pierre, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - (Mirsky), S., 1965-1969 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    - (Mirsky), V. S. (Dima), 1970-1978 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - Vasilii (Fürst W. Swiatopolk-Mirski), 1965-1970 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Taratukhin, M., 1968 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Timchenko, Nikolai, 1972 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Zoucha, 1922 (Box-folder 5: 12)
- Photographs, 1898-1977 (Boxes 5-6)
  Arrangement Statement
  Arranged alphabetically by name or subject.
  - Bazili, Nikolai Aleksandrovich, 1930-1960 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Maksimova (Maximova), Tat'iana (Tania), 1964-1968 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Nicholas II at Borodino Station on the occasion of the 100th anniversary of the Battle of Borodino, 1912 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - Russian Orthodox Church Abroad in Belgrade, 1904-1925 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ (Mirski), Georges and Jean, 1962-1972 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - Swiatopolk-Mirskia (Hanykova), Kleopatra (Kapitolina), Princess, circa 1900 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ, Mikhail Dmitrievich, Prince, 1926-1938 (Box-folder 5: 19)
  - Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ, Nikolai Ivanovich, Prince, 1898 (Box-folder 5: 20)
  - Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ, Nikolaĭ Vladimirovich, Prince, 1924-1977, undated
    Includes photographs depicting Nikolaĭ Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ, his family, and friends, arranged chronologically.
    - Undated (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - 1924-1926 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - 1936-1937 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - 1938-1939 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - 1941 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - 1944 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - 1945 (Box-folder 6: 7)
    - 1947 (Box-folder 6: 8)
    - 1949 (Box-folder 6: 9)
    - 1954 (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - 1957-1958 (Box-folder 6: 11)
    - 1960-1963 (Box-folder 6: 12)
    - 1964-1965 (Box-folder 6: 13)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 6: 14)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 6: 15)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 6: 16)
  - Svyatopolk-Mirskii, Petr (Pyotr) Dmitrievich, Prince, circa 1900 (Box-folder 6: 17)
- Writings, 1799-1976 (Boxes 6-13)
  - "L'ange de la mort" and other poems, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 6: 22)
    Includes drafts, notes, and clippings.
  - "Carmina," collection of poems, manuscripts, 1918-1947 (Box-folder 6: 18-21)
  - "Les princes Sviatopolk-Mirsky, issus de Rurik," NdR La Noblesse de Russie, deuxième edition, publiés par Nicolas Ikonnikov, Paris, 1961 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - "Les princes Sviatopolk-Mirsky (La généalogique des princes Sviatopolk-Mirsky),", 1799-1976
    Includes research material, draft chapters, correspondence, and illustrations. The files are retained as they were originally compiled and entitled by creator.
    - Research material, 1799-1976
      Includes notes, drafts, correspondence, clippings, and collected photocopies of articles and texts relating to Russian history.
      - History of Slavs (Box-folder 7: 2-6)
      - Rurik Dynasty (Box-folder 7: 7-8)
      - Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ family history (Box-folder 7: 9-16, 8: 1-3, 14: 4-5)
    - "Brouillons" (rough draft chapters), 1969-1971 (Box-folder 8: 4-12, 9: 1-7)
    - "Table des matières" (Box-folder 9: 8)
    - A. "Note liminaire" (Box-folder 9: 9)
    - B. "Préface", 1975 (Box-folder 9: 10-11)
    - C 1. "Introduction" (Box-folder 9: 12-13)
    - C 2. "Notice sur les Piast" (Box-folder 9: 14)
    - D. "Sources principales" (Box-folder 9: 15)
    - E. "Abbréviations" (Box-folder 9: 16)
    - "Observation préamble" (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - Ch. I "Examen critique des sources principales de l’histoire de la famille des princes Sviatopolk" (Box-folder 10: 2-3)
    - Ch. II "Les Skiöldung" (Box-folder 10: 4-6)
    - Ch. III "Rurikides, "Piast" (Box-folder 10: 7-8)
    - Ch. III.5 "Les alliances dynastiques des grands princes rurikides" (Box-folder 10: 9)
    - Ch. III 6a "Oleg" (Box-folder 10: 10)
    - Ch. III 6b "Igor" (Box-folder 10: 11)
    - Ch. IV "La généalogique des princes Sviatopolk-Mirsky (Russie impériale)" (Box-folder 10: 12)
    - Ch. V "Armes" (Box-folder 10: 13-16)
    - Ch. VI "Tableaux généalogiques" (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Ch. VII "La naissance de la famille des princes Sviatopolk" (Box-folder 11: 2-3)
    - Ch. VIII "Brève généalogique de la branche orthodoxe des princes Sviatopolk-Tchetvertinskiy" (Box-folder 11: 4)
    - Ch. IX "La famille des princes Sviatopolk" (Box-folder 11: 5-12, 12: 1-5)
    - Ch. IX "Biographies des enfants" (Box-folder 12: 6-8)
    - Ch. IX "Religion" (Box-folder 12: 9)
    - "Bibliographie" (Box-folder 12: 10)
    - "Annexes" (Box-folder 12: 11-12)
    - "Illustrations" (Box-folder 13: 1-9)
      Includes photographs, postcards, charts, drawings, and clippings.
    - "Index" (Box-folder 13: 10)
  - "Voyage à Bruxelles,", 1970 (Box-folder 13: 11)
- Printed Matter, 1955-1984 (Boxes 13-14)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "Biographical Dictionary of the Corps of Faces: An Outline of the Project," by Marvin Lyons, 1984 (Box-folder 13: 12)
  - Encounter: Literature Arts Current Affairs, No. 22, London, 1955 (Box-folder 13: 13)
    Includes "Comrade Prince: A Memoir of D.S. Mirsky," by Edmund Wilson.
  - Orthodox icons postcards, 1956-1976 (Box-folder 13: 14)
  - "Soiuz Pazhei," pamiatka (memo), 1960-1963 (Box-folder 14: 1-3)
- Strandmann Family Papers, 1812-1971 (Box 14)
  Consists of family papers sent from Sofia Strandmann to Nikolaĭ Vladimirovich Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ. Includes Strandmann family genealogy, correspondence, photographs, clippings, and notes, arranged chronologically.
  - 1812-1817 (Box-folder 14: 6)
  - 1827 (Box-folder 14: 7)
  - 1833-1839 (Box-folder 14: 8)
  - 1874-1899 (Box-folder 14: 9)
  - 1904-1911 (Box-folder 14: 10)
  - 1912-1918 (Box-folder 14: 11)
  - 1929-1939 (Box-folder 14: 12)
  - 1954-1971 (Box-folder 14: 13)
- Oversize Material, 1802-1971 (Boxes 15-16)
  Arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Legal papers, 1886-1930 (Box-folder 15: 1-5)
    Princess Maria Aleksandrovna Svi͡atopolk-Mirskiĭ (Mirskaia)'s documents in the possession of the Lavriki estate in the region of Kiev, in Ukraine. Includes maps and drawings.
  - Lithographs, Imperial Russian Army Cossack regiments, 1802-1900 (Box-folder 15: 6-7)
  - Memoirs, manuscript by "Sasha',", 1971 (Box 16)